James Gross NLRB Files /4057
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series III. NATIONAL LABOR RELATIONS BOARD 7/35-11/47
  - Sub-Series A. NATIONAL LABOR RELATIONS BOARD RECORDS
    - Sub-Series 2. CORRESPONDENCE 7/19/35-3/19/70
      - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 3)
        8/16/37-8/31/37; Stephen Early correspondence concerning House appropriations; correspondence relating to the accusation that the NLRB favors the C.I.O., particularly with respect to the National Electric Products Corp. cases VI-C-84 and VI-R-17, includes Benjamin E. Gordon's (Region 6) request that the case be re-opened; the President's refusal of an invitation to the National Federation of Federal Employees convention and his approval of a provision in their constitution prohibiting Federal Employees from bargaining collectively and forbidding them to engage in or support strikes (provision attached); Senator Edward R. Burke's attack on the NLRB includes a press release and the text of his speech before the National Grange; records of Madden's telephone conversations with Hugh Thompson (Regional Director of C.I.O in Buffalo) discussing the Buffalo Packing Case, and with Joe Ozanic (President, Progressive Miners) and A.D. Lewis discussing Mine B Coal Co.; A.F. of L.- C.I.O. conflict resulting in the shutdown of seven Portland, Oregon sawmills of which Jones Lumber Co. and West Oregon Lumber Co. were two, includes: 4 telegrams to Morris Jones (Jones Lumber Co.) from J.F. Cambiano (President, The Cal. State Council of Carpenters), A.V. Walker (Business Agent, Millmens Local 1348, United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America), A.W. Hughes (Business Representative, Lumber and Sawmill Workers Local 2708), C.R. Van Winkle (Secretary,Los Angeles County District Council of Carpenters) stating they will boycott products manufactured under C.I.O.; a letter from A.E. McIntosh (President, West Oregon Lumber Co.) to Claude M. Hale (President, Lumber and Sawmill Workers Union, Local 3) stating the shutdown is due to fighting between labor factions, not a lockout; correspondence reporting on the Hoffman Beverage Co., and Joint Local Executive Board of the International Union of United Brewery Workers of America, case R-214; economic material relating to the Motion Picture cases XXI-R-149-158; Republic Creosoting Co. case XI-C-122; David Persinger and Douglas Aircraft Co. Inc. cases XXI-C-183, XXI-C-220.
      - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 4)
        9/1/37-9/29/37; Correspondence relating to A.F.of L.- C.I.O conflict from Saposs and Hope; from Madden and Burke concerning anti-NLRB sentiment and propaganda, and from D.L. Kelly (W.Va. Representative, National Electric Products Corp.) to the President as well as a reply from James Roosevelt (Secretary to the President); from Joseph P. Ryan (President, International Longshoremen's Association) to the President about Edwin S. Smith; the Republic Steel strike and Steelworkers Organizing Committee (SWOC); the Cudahy Packing Co. case XVII-R-17 and violations of Sec. 8(2); narrative account of hearing in the Newport News Shipping & Dry Dock Co. case; Saposs' analysis of respondent's presentation on written, signed agreements in the Inland case; R.D. Stevenson's account of employer intimidation and discriminatory discharge in the Seagrove Corp. case; new hearing suggested in the Montgomery Wards and Co. cases; John T. Lindsay`s discussion of evidence by inference with regard to the Youngstown Sheet and Tube Co case.; Jacob Billikopf's (Executive Director, National Coordinating Committee for Aid to Refugees and Emigrants Coming from Germany) opposition to the popular sentiment that sees the NLRB as persecuting industry; Blankenhorn's discussion of the following: Lewis' political position; requests for information on vigilantism, espoinage and company unions, and the LaFollette hearings, specifically Officials of the Railway Act and the Pinkertons; A.B. Hawes' (Actg. Asst. General Counsel) recommendation of a "write in" space on the ballot; Fahy's refusal to take jurisdiction of cases involving the repair or building of highways used in interstate travel or transportation; Edwin S. Smith's description of the Philadelphia office as "perfect chaos".
      - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 5)
        10/1/37-10/30/37; Correspondence relating to the Maritime elections, specifically the Waterman Steamship Co. and American France Line, includes Witt's explanation of the Board's position on maritine elections; Mary L. Schleifer's (Attorney) discussion of discrimination between unions issuing passes; Joseph M. Curran's (General Organizer, National Maritime Union of America) opposition to the inclusion of tugs and barges in the balloting order; A.F. of L.-C.I.O. conflict and election results, press release in the Globe Machine and Stamping Co. cases R-178 - 180; Hope's report of personal threats reporting on intimidation, coercion and a company dominated union in the California Walnut Growers Association case XXI-C-439 and XXI-R-347; proposed contempt proceedings in NLRB versus Pacific Greyhound Lines; Blakenhorn mentions the Daily Worker will print Green, Woll, Frey and Easley letters; letter to Perkins about David Moskovitz, the Communist Party, and the Yale Mfg. Co.; administrative correspondence includes: Fahy on complaints; Wolf on instruction to trial examiners; and Madden to Fahy about his meeting with Congressman Louis Ludlow.
      - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 6)
        11/4/37-11/30/37; Memo of conference between the NLRB and the Wisconsin Labor Relations Board on the administration of the Wisconsin Labor Relations Act; correspondence reporting on the American France et al R-157 (the Cosmopolitan Shipping Co., Inc.) with clippings discussing Senator Guffey's Maritime bill; distribution of propaganda to voters in the National Sugar Refining Co.; distablishment of the A.F.ofL. union in the Eagle- Picher case; Judge Maur rules in favor of Mr. Ford in the Ford Motor Co. case; question of lawyers active in formimg company unions appearing before the Board in the Union Drawn Steel Co. case VI-C-160 and related cases; correspondence relating to A.F. ofL.-C.I.O. conflict includes possible statement to be used in address before the Mayors Conference; Joseph K. Carson Jr. (Mayor, City of Portland) contending the Board has no jurisdiction in the Portland Lumber controversy and other related correspondence.
      - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 7)
        12/1/37-12/29/37; Correspondence reporting on the Yates American Machine Co. case XII-C-68 and the union's failure to file a charge against the employer; the field examiner's conduct in the Swift and Co. cases XI-C-149, XI-R-51; Judge Padway's position in the Allis-Chalmers case XII-R-40; Edwin S. Smith's dissent in the Combustion Engineering Co. case; Fahy on arguments in the Consolidated Edison case; question of language in the Waterbury Mfg. Co. decision; possibility of Dudley (Trial Examiner) filing prejury charge against union witness in Union Drawn Steel Co. case; lockout in the Ford case; discussion of licensed and unlicensed personnel on the Grace Lines Inc. case R-157, R-110; economic data in the Liggett Drug Co. case I-C-413; the Portland Lumber controversy; the American France et al case R-157 and Harry Bridges; amendments to the Wagner Bill (includes discussion of LaFollette's amendments, Garrision's suggestions and the Burke Resolution;) Madden to Hon. Fred Bierman (U.S. House of Representatives) refuting the charge the NLRB is C.I.O. controlled; Green's contention that longshoremen do not have jurisdiction over warehousemen and mill workers; Blakenhorn's "Congressmen and Freedom of the Press" and the ACLU's support of the Board's position; Madden's and George Googe's discussion of the Mobile Steamship Association (the Alabama Longshoremen's situation) specifically closed-shop contracts, contains an example of institutional racism.
      - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 8)
        1/5/38-1/31/38; Correspondence reporting on the American Sugar Refining Co. case R-364; the Ford Motor Co.; the American France Line et al case R-157; National Electric Products Corp. and closed shop agreement; A.F. of L.- C.I.O. conflict; the Weirton Steel Co. case; and the Shipowners Association of the Pacific Coast, Waterfront Employers Association of the Pacific Coast, et al and the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union, Dis. 1, case XX-R-196; Herrick's discussion of the educational effect of the NLRB and the Wagner Act on management; President's request for a memo on the development of industrial relations and policies; appropriations; the Investigation of the NLRB by the Senate Judiciary Committee (the Burke Resolution, S. Res. 207), including 6 personal and confidential memos from regional directors advising Witt of complaints brought against their boards; a letter from Madden to Hon. J. Hamilton Lewis (U.S.Senate) saying the investigation will disclose nothing.
      - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 9)
        2/2/38-2/28/38; Correspondence concerning the ILA (includes a discussion of Ryan's testimony before the Senate Commerce Committee, a reference to a" communist regime" in Lawrence, Madden's letter to Senator Vandenberg, and Calkins, Levy correspondence); Taft's (CTU) discussion of the Postal Telegraph Cable Co.; letter to Elbert D. Thomas (Chairman, Committee on Education and Labor) regarding S.3390 (guaranties of collective bargaining); Gilbert Montague to Edwin Schoenfeld (Forum Division, Adult Educational Program, Board of Education, New York City) refusing to appear on a program with Elinor Herrick; Margaret Bennett on secret preferential shop contracts in the Electric Vacuun Cleaner Co. Inc., and United Electrical and Radio Workers of America.
      - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 10)
        3/1/38-3/31/38; Correspondence reporting on the Electric Boat case C-165 and the Remington Rand case; the California Nut Growers' Association; Youngstown Sheet and Tube Co. C-191; National Electric Products Corp. VI-C-84; and Iowa Southern Utilities Co. XIII-C-407; Hope to Stern about the Portland Lumber cases; hearings conducted by the NLRB in Spartanburg, S.C. including a letter to Congressman Mahon from Fahy; personal and confidential memo from Witt on the Seattle Office, criticizing the director; Harold A. Cranefield's discussion of Free Press and Judge George W. Sample, clippings attached.
      - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 11)
        4/6/38-4/30/38; Correspondence reporting on the Republic Creosoting Co. XI-C-122 and reinstatement; comments on current Illinois labor situation, specifically the recall to work of Memorial Day protesters; the Shepard Line election; enforcement order against Jacobs Bros. Co. Inc., C-244; petition of Bethlehem Steel Co. to vacate denial of applications for subpoenas, C-170, R-177; enforcement of order against Stackpole Carbon Co. C- 232; rehearing and reinstatement in the Mooresville Cotton Mills, C-195; the conduct of hearings including Fahy on "length"; record of the Percut-Richards Packing Co. et al: California Processors and Growers, Inc. and United Cannery, Agricultural, Packing and Allied Workers of America, cases XX-C-362-377; Madden's and Mr. Calvin's (Metal Trades Dept.) discussion of the Todd Shipyards; Blakenhorn's discussion of the aim of Burke's activities.
      - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 12)
        5/2/38-5/31/38; Letter from Logan on policy with respect to the Mobile situation and Harry Bridges (4pp); correspondence reporting on the Alaska Juneau Gold Mining Co. C-91; Ford Motor Co. III-C-83; Pacific Mills aiding and abetting the Waumbec Co. I-C-715; American France Line and the International Sailor's Union (ISU);California Walnut Growers Association XXI-C-439, XXI-R-347; Todd Johnson Drydocks, Inc.; enforcement in the Indianapolis; Glove Co. C-251; order of certification be withdrawn in the Alaska Packers Association R-716; discriminatory discharge and settlement in the Kelly Springfield Tire Co. C-315; press release of Madden's statement to the Senate Committee on the Judiciary on H.R. 9745; Witt's discussion of regional offices on the Pacific Coast; Elliott's discussion of integration of black and white longshoremen in the NMU; Pratt on the working arrangement of trial examiners, with attached tables; Witt's discussion of the attitude of employers on majority question in 8(5) cases; Senator Clyde Herring's criticism of Herbert Vogt of the Chicago office; Blakenhorn's report on LaFollette Committee appropriation; Madden's and Homer Martin's discussion of the General Motors situation; J.R. Robinson`s (C.I.O. Southern California Region) claim of evidence of collusions between the Director of Region 21, and the A.F.of L.; James P. Miller's (Region 8) description of violent confrontation in the Goodyear and Akron situation; personal and confidential memo from Nathaniel Clark on Isadore Komarff reporting "excellent quality" of work.
      - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 13)
        6/1/38-6/30/38; Correspondence reporting on unauthorized sit-down strike in the Celanese Corp. of America V-C-414, V-R-14,16; violations of 8(2) in the Eagle-Picher case; discrepancy in procedure in the Pittsburg Plate Glass Co. XIV-C-174, VI-R-91; California Cotton Corp. XXI-C-525, XXV-C-666 (14pp); Republic Steel Corp.; Shell Oil of California R-551; Swift and Co. XVIII-C-161 (8 pp); Weirton Steel Co. (11pp); Paul Herzog's (Chairman, New York State Labor Relations Board) survey of employer election petitions files with his board (6/1/37-8/1/37); Boris Shishkin's (A.F. of L.) criticism of the President; Blankehorn on reorganization of LaFollette files; Madden's and Senator Hill's discussion of the Cherry Cotton Mills decision; Lawrence Clayton (Assistant to the Chairman, Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System) on Board files on the TransAmerica Corp. and the Bank of America, N.T. & S.A.; Herman Edelsberg's statement that Edmund Toland (Attorney for Mathieson Alkali) will not allow his witnesses to be examined by Edelsberg, clippings attached; Feildelson to Edwin S. Smith on the Boards position with the press; confidential letter from Shishkin with information on British Strikes; Robert M. Gates' (Region 21) discussion of C.I.O. complaints on cases (21pp); Logan's discussion of homelife, ILA, NMU, the ILWU; Joseph Ryan's charge that the NLRB shows favoritism with respect to the ILWU and the New Orleans situation; Watts to Hon. Robert H. Jackson, Solicitor General about NLRB versus Columbian Enameling and Stamping Co. Inc.; Fred G. Krivonos (Special Examiner) on problems with the New York office; Gates' discussion of problems with the Los Angeles Office, especially Brown and Pomerance; Witt's impatience with Herrick over the Pioneer Baking Co. II-C-1624.
      - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 14)
        7/1/38-7/30/38; Correspondence reporting on the Bank of America XXI-C-570 and a question of jurisdiction; the fabrication of evidence in the Thompson Products Inc. case (5pp); SWOC's charge against the E.T. Fraim Lock Co. IV-R-198; Consolidated Aircraft election R-761; violation of 8(1),(3) in the New York Times case II-C-1112; heated Madden/Herrick discussion of procedure; Harry Bridges' question on contract status; Witt on investigation of 8(2) cases; Frank Bowen (Director, Region 7) on the U.A.W.A. situation; John J. Babe's recommendation for enforcement in the Sterling Electric Motors case C-415; substantive memo from VanArkel on reopening the Republic Steel Corp. case C-184 (6pp); Emerson's discussion of Maritime Commission Policy regarding licensed and unlicensed personnel, open shop, etc.; summary of conferences, mediations, deliberations and investigations in the Portland Lumber Mills case.
      - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 15)
        8/1/38-8/31/38; Correspondence reporting on Texas Co. II-C1761, Pure Oil Co. II-C-1763, Cities Service Oil Co. II-C-1761 and Continental Oil Co. II-C-1767 recommending a hearing; Pittsburgh Plate Glass Co. XIV-C-174 (VI-R-91); Alston Coal XVIII-R-84 and collusion between the employer and UMW; excerpt from "A Presumptious Ruling", Michigan Manufacturer and Financial Record; personal and confidential letter from Witt to Nylander about C.I.O. complaint in the Taylor Milling Corp. case; Witt on the necessity for reducing number of cases which go to hearing; Fahy to Robert Jackson stating the "court erred" in Fansteel versus NLRB decision; Gallup Poll on the Wagner Labor Act and related issues; Lee Loevinger on Robert J. Wiener and Swift & Co. XVII-C-161; Eagen's recommendation for an investigation in the Walla Walla Heat and Cold Storage Co. situation; a letter to Robert Wohlfort discussing an investigation of anti-union activities in the Northwest region; NLRB's vote to affiliate with the Washington Friends Spanish Democracy; Stern on field staff fraternizing with union groups; A.F.of L. opposition to Donald Wakefield Smith's reappointment to the Board; Weirton Steel Co. et al VI-C-74, order 8/6/34 refusal of petition to vacate trial examiner's order for issuance of subpoenas; Congressman Celler's and Julius Schlezinger's (President, Lawyers' Union of the NLRB) discussion of trial examiners; John L. Smith (Treasurer, National Council of Independent Unions) to the President on changes in the Labor Act; Madden's and Carter's discussion of C.I.O. violation of stipulations in the New Orleans situation.
      - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 16)
        9/2/38-9/30/38; Grenville Clark's (Chairman, Committee of the American Bar Association, Bill of Rights Committee) request for access to files relating to the supression free speech and freedom of the press; Labor Day speech of Joseph Padway; Saposs' recommended study of sit-down strikes (Fansteel); A.F. of L.'s bitterness in the California Brewers situation; Indianapolis Glove Co. C-251 and 8(2) violations; John H. Dorsey's discussion of weakness in the Waggoner Refining Co.Inc. C-230; Harry Wilson's (Ph.D. student, Northwestern University) request to study the trial examiner staff of the NLRB; C.I.O's review of procedure followed in filing complaint cases under the NLRA; the Waterfront Employers and ILWU membership in Olympia, Wa; Remington Rand; more trouble with Herrick; "Encouragement for Cardenas", The Journal of Commerce, and related correspondence between the President, Edwin S. Smith and Arthur Vandenberg; authorization and order for investigation and hearing in the National Sugar Refining Co. II-R-1076; David Shaw on intervention in 8(2) cases.
      - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 17)
        10/1/38-10/31/38; Witt to H.P. Melnikow (Pacific Coast Labor Bureau) recommending a neutral person check membership list in the ILWU; elections in the Sheel Oil Co. R-551; A. Sartorius and Co. R-995 and voting eligibility; the Minneapolis office (8pp); LaFollette Committee's investigation of the West Coast Employers' Association and possible civil rights violations; Madden to Senator Clyde Herring on Herbert J. Vogt; Dorothea de Schweinitz's discussion of William Green and related issues; correspondence to the President on NLRB handling of cases involving the A.F.of L. and the C.I.O. (15pp); Lawrence Hunt on the New Orleans Longshoremen's election (24pp); Lawyers Union of the NLRB on the issue of wage increase; continued correspondence from Harry Wilson; Cowdrill's discussion of the Progressive Miners Association; Madden to the editor of The Journal of the Electrical Workers and Operators about "winchellism"; significant correspondence relating to the Gulf Longshoremen's election, and discharge policy in the New Orleans and Mobile cases; correspondence relating to the agenda for the Washington Conference (30pp+).
      - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 18)
        11/1/38-11/30/38; Correspondence relating to the Regional Conference and Washington Staff Conference (50pp+); Madden's and Tom Coleman's (AP) discussion of amendments to the Act; annotated memo to the President from Madden on employees petitioning for a vote of directors or stockholders; clipping from David Lawrence concerning amending the NLRA and the Botany Worsted case; correspondence related to Wilson's study includes a list of trial examiners; Elliott on Maury Maverick appropriations; The International Juridical Association pamphlet "NLRB and Free Speech"; alleged statement in National Cash Register Co. IX-C-439; Lawrence's (UP) and Madden's discussion of employers' right to ask for an election; Charles Persons' discussion of his resignation; summary of administrative problems involving regional and executive boards by Feidelson and Herrick (Directors of Regional Conference); Blakenhorn on the C.I.O. convention and LaFollette Committee legislation; more correspondence on "winchellism"; Vogt to Donald Wakefield Smith about Senator Herring and related matters; Edwin S. Smith's discussion of an amendment to the rules of the Board allowing employers to file petitions; R.N. Deham's essay about employer's attitude toward the Board.
      - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 19)
        12/2/38-12/30/38; Correspondence reporting on a representation issue in the Heldman-Schild, Inc. IX- R-268, and the Heldman-Schild-Lasser Co. cases; amendments to the Act - suggestions by trial examiner Denham; Edwin S. Smith's address "The Wagner Act and Labor Relations" before the Massachusetts Conference of Social Work, with related correspondence to the President; Saposs' "the bargaining unit of the International Association of Machinists" (15pp); Lee Pressman's and Tony Smith's advice on certain action in the Thompson Products C-190; Saposs' discussion of the Supreme Court Brief in Fansteel Metallurgical Corp C-235, and Seatrain Lines Inc. ll-C-74, R-157; Blakenhorn's update on the LaFollette Committee Investigation.
      - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 20)
        1/2/39-1/30/39; Correspondence relating to Maston Roberts' (Recording Secretary, UMWA Local 6430) request that the President oppose changes in the Wagner Act; Herrick's criticism of Witts' "Function of Special Examiner", and other Herrick/Witt correspondence; correspondence between Edwin S. Smith and the President concerning the American League for Peace and Democracy; information concerning NLRB field activity in the American Rolling Mills Co. IX-C-530; confidential memo from Blankenhorn on LaFollette Committee Programs; discriminatory discharge in New York Times C-795; the oral argument in A.F.of L., ILA versus NLRB (7257); R.N. Dehnam to James C. Batten (First Co-chairman, Trial Examiners Association) on the function of the trial examiner; John L. Lewis to the President about government contracts; L. Cunningham's (Financial Secretary, Fresh Fruit and Vegetable Workers Local 78 UCAPAWA, CIO) discussion of Nylander; Trial Examiners Association regarding salary increases.
      - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 21)